RUSTAM ISANGULOV

SOFTWARE ENGINEER | SOFTWARE ARCHITECT | OCP JAVA 11 | PHD

PROFILE

15+ years of experience in software development, progressing from a software engineer to a program architect position. It includes 9+ years of working in a Research and Development environment on data processing and planning for automation projects. 6+ years of experience in management and product management in a multi-national corporate environment and in the context of a small startup.

EXPERIENCE

PRODUCT MANAGER, INTELLISENSE.IO, CAMBRIDGE UK - 2020-2021

Developed product roadmaps, feature specifications and requirements for the brains.app (an industrial SaaS AI platform); Managed effective product delivery by the "platform" scrum team (~12 engineers) to internal and external clients.

SOLUTIONS ANALYST, SCHLUMBERGER, BEIJING CHINA – 2018-2020

Performed analysis of automated planning needs for the well engineering platform (DrillPlan) and investigated potential applications of classical Al planning to improve consistency and procedural adherence.

PROJECT MANAGER, SCHLUMBERGER, HOUSTON USA - 2015-2018

Managed a team of ~12 engineers with the goal to deliver new decision management and execution system for drilling fluids workflows. On the technical side, I was responsible for multi-domain logical inference design to ensure the new product is well integrated with the drilling automation (see below) and a higher level workflow orchestration systems.

PROGRAM ARCHITECT, SCHLUMBERGER, HOUSTON USA - 2013-2015

Created the vision, defined technical direction and architecture, and guided technology stack choices for the drilling automation system that is now a part of the well-construction platform (DrillOps). Collaborated with ~30 engineers in the team to ensure a shared understanding of the vision and the plan-based automation architecture.

SENIOR DEVELOPMENT ENGINEER, SCHLUMBERGER RESEARCH CENTER,

CAMBRIDGE UK - 2004-2013

Developed a number of research projects in the Monitoring and Control Group, mainly concerned with drilling automation, process optimisation and classical AI planning. I have conducted field experiments (to test proof of concept systems) in several locations including Poza Rica, Mexico; Basra, Iraq; Abu Dhabi, UAE.

SOFTWARE ENGINEER, SCHLUMBERGER, HOUSTON USA - 2000-2004

Developed several commercial software packages as a sole software engineer and as a member of small teams, mainly for seismic and downhole data processing and visualisation.

EDUCATION

Imperial College London, UK — PhD, Applied Mathematics - 2005 - 2009

Moscow State Technological University "Stankin", Russia — Engineering Diploma (~MS), CAD/CAM Systems & Applied Mathematics - 1992 - 1998

SKILLS

- Oracle Certified Professional Java SE 11 Developer (28 May 2022)
- Java / JUnit 5 / Mockito / Maven / Spring / Spring Boot
- C# / Matlab / C++ / SQL / Python
- Rational UML Modelling / Planning Domain Definition Language
- Git / Aha! / Jira / Microsoft VSTS

PATENTS

- Systems and methods for executing a plan associated with multiple equipment by using rule-based inference (US11288609B2)
- Well Construction Management and Decision Support System (US10920565B2)
- Automated sliding drilling (US10883356B2)
- Method and system for directional drilling (US10612307B2)
- Method for calculating and displaying optimized drilling operating parameters and for characterizing drilling performance with respect to performance benchmarks (US10316653B2)

PUBLICATIONS

- Optimizing ROP through automation (Drilling Contractor, Sep 21 2011)
- Increased Rate of Penetration Through Automation (SPE-139897-MS)
- A mathematical model of an oil and gas field development process (European Journal of Applied Mathematics, Mar 8 2010)

CAMBRIDGE, UK

EMAIL: RUSTAM.ISANGULOV@ME.COM

LINKEDIN: WWW.LINKEDIN.COM/IN/RUSTAM-ISANGULOV